A Guide to the Thomas Perkins Abernethy Papers, 1800-1970
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Thomas Perkins Abernethy Papers 1800-1970
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12765-b
This collection consists of ca. 1550 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was presented to the library on November 11, 1974 by Thomas Perkins Abernethy, 39 University Circle, Charlottesville, Virginia, through Mrs. Charles M. Davison, Jr., 1856 Edgewood Lane, Charlottesville, Virginia.
Biographical/Historical Information
A biographical note about Thomas Perkins Abernethy has been included in the guide to #6464-a.
Ida (Robertson) Abernethy was born on August 6, 1891, in Charleston, South Carolina. She received a B.A. in education from Winthrop College in Rock Hill, South Carolina. She and Thomas Perkins Abernethy were married on December 6, 1917. Mrs. Abernethy wrote a number of articles and short stories, many of which were published in newspapers and periodicals. She died on May 21, 1969.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the Thomas Perkins Abernethy Collection consists of approximately 1,550 items (4 2/3 linear feet) which range in date from 1800-1970, although the bulk of hte material falls within hte twentieth century. Like the preceding addition to the collection, there is much correspondence with fellow historians (Frederick Jackson Turner, Hilaire Belloc, and Esmond Wright, among others) and Abernethy's graduate students (such as Darrett Rutman) as well as correspondence about Ablernethy's books. There are also several manuscripts of articles and book reviews by Abernethy and numerous periodicals, pamphlets, and reprints of articles by other historians. Unlike #6464-a, however, this new addition contains a great deal of personal correspondence between Abernethy and his wife Ida (Robertson) Abernethy, with other members of his family, and with friends. Correspondence concerning personal business matters, an extensive assortment of newspaper clippings concerning segregation, and the manuscripts of several articles by Ida (Robertson) Abernethy round out the collection.
This collection complements the material in the two previous accessions, #6464 and #6464-a, because it includes much personal correspondence. However, with the exception of drafts of The South In the New Nation located in collections #6464 and #6464-a, the manuscripts of his books are missing.
Arrangement
Arrangement
When the collection arrived at the library, it was in rough chronological order. For this reason, a chronological arrangement was retained.
Organization
Abernethy's professional correspondence, that is, letters from sutdents and colleagues in the historical profession, as well as letters concerning Abernethy's publications, have been separated from the rest of the correspondence and placed at the beginning of the collection. The professional correspondence is followed by personal correspondence, Abernethy's articles and book reviews, research material, Ida (Robertson) Abernethy's writings, and miscellaneous papers. Newspaper clippings, pamphlets, reprints of articles, and periodicals are found at the end of the collection.
Contents List
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy 1910, 1911, 1916, 3 items (Box 1)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy 1921-1924, 30 items (Box 1)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy 1926-1929, 13 items (Box 1)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy 1930-1939, ca. 40 items. (Box 1)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy 1940-1949, ca. 80 items (Box 1)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy 1950-1952, ca. 25 items. (Box 1)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy 1953, ca. 80 items (Box 1)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy 1954-1956, ca. 60 items (Box 1)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy 1957-1959, ca. 30 items (Box 1)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy 1960-1961, 1969, 27 items (Box 2)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. Abernethy May-Dec. & n. d., 12 items (Box 2)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1912-1917 Sept., 32 items (Box 2)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1917 Oct.-1918 July, 28 items (Box 2)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1918 Aug.-1919, 13 items (Box 2)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1920-1937, 25 items (Box 2)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1940-1943, 25 items (Box 2)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1944-1949, 22 items (Box 2)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1950-1952, 24 items (Box 3)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1953-1954, 28 items (Box 3)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1955-1956, 38 items (Box 3)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1957-1958, 31 items (Box 3)
- Professional Correspondence of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1959-1961 & n. d., 29 items (Box 3)
- Articles, Speeches and Book Reviews by T. P. Abernethy 1924, 1953, 1957-1958, n. d., 12 items (Box 3)
- Book Reviews, Contracts, News Releases and Miscellaneous Papers concerning Abernethy's books ca. 1935-1954, 11 items (Box 3)
- Transcript of portions of letters of Andrew Jackson to Gen. John Coffee and to Andrew J. Hutchings; also transcript of letter of Benjamin J. Wysor to James M. Reyburn 1831-1832 & 1835, 2 items (Box 4)
- Economic Map Studies of the South based on the Manufacturers' Census of 1810 and the Federal Population Censuses of 1790, 1800 and 1810; also Map of Vote on Virginia Resolutions in House of Delegates, 1798 1940 & n. d., 23 items (Box 4)
- Articles by Ida (Robertson) Abernethy n. d., ca. 15 items (Box 4)
- Articles by Ida (Robertson) Abernethy n. d., ca. 13 items (Box 4)
- Drafts of article by Ida (Robertson) Abernethy on Theater in Colonial Virginia with photographs of actors n. d., 4 items (Box 4)
- Short Stories, Plays, Poems by Ida (Robertson) Abernethy n. d., 7 items (Box 4)
- Military Papers of T. P. Abernethy 1918, 1922, 1924, & n. d., 16 items (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Papers of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1924, 1929, 1936, 1943-1959, 1971 & n. d., ca. 40 items. (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Souvenirs of T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy: Programs, Certificates, Calling Cards, etc. 1920, 1940-1960, & n. d., ca. 30 items (Box 4)
- Genealogy: Robertson Family Records by J. Montgomery Seaver 1928, 1 item (Box 4)
- Postcards and Photographs of U. Va. Campus; also photograph of T. P. Abernethy's room at Harvard n. d., 10 items (Box 4)
- Woodcuts: "Die Marquise" Holzschnitt von Ernst Dombrowski ["The Marquise" Woodcut by Ernst Dombrowski]; "Auf der Treppe" Holzschnitt von Ernst Dombrowski ["On the Staircase" Woodcut by Ernst Dombrowski] n. d., 2 items (Box 4)
- Periodicals with Articles re: T. P. Abernethy 1959 & 1961, 6 items (Box 4)
- Newspaper Clippings concerning T. P. and Ida (Robertson) Abernethy 1927, 1959, & n. d., 7 items (Box 5)
- Newspaper Clippings re: Family, Friends, Colleagues 1943-1956 & n. d., 16 items (Box 5)
- Newspaper Clippings re: American History 1922, 1934-1936, 1956-1957, 1961, & n. d., 15 items (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous Newspaper and Periodical Clippings, primarily recipes 1950, 1956-1960, & n. d., ca. 70 items (Box 5)
- Newspaper Clippings primarily concerning Segregation 1945, 1950, & 1955-1957, ca. 50 items (Box 5)
- Newspaper Clippings primarily concerning Segregation 1958-1960, 22 items (Box 5)
- Newspaper Clippings primarily concerning Segregation n. d., ca. 100 items (Box 5)
- Newspaper Clippings primarily concerning Segregation n. d., ca. 70 items (Box 5)
- Newspaper Clippings primarily concerning Segregation n. d., ca. 90 items (Box 5)
- Pamphlets and Miscellaneous Printed Material re: Segregation 1954-1956, 26 items (Box 5)
- Pamphlets and Miscellaneous Printed Material re: Segregation 1957, ca. 25 items. (Box 5)
- Pamphlets and Miscellaneous Printed Material re: Segregation 1958-1959 & n. d., 19 items (Box 6)
- A Petition of Cato West, a report to a committee of the whole House of Representatives 1800, 1 item (Box 6)
- The Several Petitions of Thomas Buring and Others, a report to a committee of the whole House of Representatives 1800, 1 item (Box 6)
- Melodies, Songs, Sacred Songs, And National Airs by Thomas Moore, Esq. 1838, 1 item (Box 6)
- Laurie Todd's Notes on Virginia with a Chapter on Puritans, Witches and Friends by Grant Thorburn 1848, 1 item (Box 6)
- Curiosity Visits To Southern Plantations by a Northern man 1863, 1 item (Box 6)
- Southern Sketches, Cevil Gray; or the Soldier's Revenge Rosa Sherwood; or the Avenger by Mrs. Helena J. Harris 1866, 1 item (Box 6)
- Representation In Virginia by Julian A. C. Chandler 1896, 1 item (Box 6)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: American History 1882, 1901, 1905, & 1921, 4 items (Box 6)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: American History 1924-1926, 4 items (Box 6)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: American History 1929, 1932-1934, 6 items (Box 6)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: American History 1935-1937, 8 items (Box 7)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: American History 1938-1939, 4 items (Box 7)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: American History 1940-1941, 9 items (Box 7)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: American History 1942-1943, 11 items (Box 7)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: American History 1944-1945, 11 items (Box 7)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: American History 1946-1949, 9 items (Box 8)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: American History 1950-1953, 12 items (Box 8)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: American History 1954-1956, 10 items (Box 8)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: American History 1957-1959, 12 items (Box 8)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: American History 1960-1961, & 1970, 6 items (Box 8)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: American History n. d., 12 items (Box 9)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: Miscellaneous Topics 1916, 1920, 1925, 1945, 1950-1952, & 1961, 9 items (Box 9)
- Pamphlets and Reprints from Periodicals re: Miscellaneous Topics n. d., 4 items (Box 9)
- Books and Periodicals re: American History 1924, 1931-1947, 13 items (Box 9)
- Books and Periodicals re: American History; also cookbook 1947-1959, 17 items (Box 10)
- Books and Periodicals re: American History 1960-1968, 13 items (Box 11)